<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Nadjet&#39;s NLP Stuff</title>
    <link>https://nadjet.github.io/blog/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Nadjet&#39;s NLP Stuff</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 20 Nov 2021 20:17:02 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://nadjet.github.io/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>My cherry-picked highlights from the EMNLP&#39;21 Conference</title>
      <link>https://nadjet.github.io/blog/posts/emnlp_2021_report/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Nov 2021 20:17:02 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nadjet.github.io/blog/posts/emnlp_2021_report/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A couple of weeks ago I attended virtually the EMNLP&#39;2021 Conference. This is the first time I attend a conference virtually. I must admit this is not without its advantages: cheaper registration fees, no Jet-Lag, the ability to get your brain blasted in the comfort of your own home, the ability to switch between sessions much more quickly than if it was in a physical setting, as well as in my experience, a more &amp;ldquo;intimate&amp;rdquo; one-to-one interaction during the poster sessions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the negative side, technical network problems meant the presentations were often recorded with no time for questions, and the likeliness that you will bump into someone you know is less likely, although I enjoyed &amp;ldquo;stalking&amp;rdquo; presenters to their poster rooms in &amp;ldquo;Gather Town&amp;rdquo;, the virtual conference venue :-)&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some interesting talks I &amp;ldquo;attended&amp;rdquo; at the conference, organized by topic:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data Science Projects (Q1-2022)</title>
      <link>https://nadjet.github.io/blog/posts/masters_topics_q1_2022/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Jul 2021 14:18:55 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nadjet.github.io/blog/posts/masters_topics_q1_2022/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This first quarter of the 2021-2022 academic year, I supervise 5 final year projects in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://estudios.uoc.edu/es/masters-universitarios/data-science/presentacion&#34;&gt;Data Science Master&lt;/a&gt; of the UOC University, three of which in &amp;ldquo;general&amp;rdquo; domains which are 1) &lt;a href=&#34;#1-argument-mining&#34;&gt;argument mining&lt;/a&gt;, 2) &lt;a href=&#34;#2-wikipedia&#34;&gt;mining of encyclopedic knowledge from wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;, 3) &lt;a href=&#34;#3-anonym&#34;&gt;text anonymization&lt;/a&gt;, and two of which in applied domains that are 4) use of &lt;a href=&#34;#4-medical&#34;&gt;NLP in an online medical consultation application&lt;/a&gt;, and 5) &lt;a href=&#34;#5-defects&#34;&gt;detection of recurrent defects in aircraft safety reports&lt;/a&gt;. Below is a selection of the resources and references I give to the students to get them started (sorry, the bibliographical citations are a bit sloppy).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sentence similarity with Bert vs SBert</title>
      <link>https://nadjet.github.io/blog/posts/sentence_similarity/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Oct 2020 21:48:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nadjet.github.io/blog/posts/sentence_similarity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We can compute the similarity between two sentences by calculating the similarity between their embeddings. A popular approach is to perform the mean or max averaging of the sentence word embeddings. Another approach, which is faster and more performant, is to use SBert models.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data Science Projects (Q1-2021)</title>
      <link>https://nadjet.github.io/blog/posts/masters_topics_q1_2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Oct 2020 12:11:38 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nadjet.github.io/blog/posts/masters_topics_q1_2021/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This first quarter of the 2020-2021 academic year, I supervise 6 final year projects in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://estudios.uoc.edu/es/masters-universitarios/data-science/presentacion&#34;&gt;Data Science Master&lt;/a&gt; of the UOC University, ranging from the development of a COVID-19 FAQ-based Q-A system to building knowledge graphs and performing end-to-end Natural Language Generation. Below is a list of resources and references I offer to get the students started.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Aspect Based Sentiment Analysis</title>
      <link>https://nadjet.github.io/blog/posts/absa/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Apr 2020 14:34:18 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nadjet.github.io/blog/posts/absa/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this post I report on &lt;a href=&#34;#approaches&#34;&gt;approaches to ABSA&lt;/a&gt; as a Bert Sentence Pair Classification (BERT-SPC) problem together with domain adaptation of the Bert language model (BERT-ADA). I also present my &lt;a href=&#34;#experiments&#34;&gt;implementation&lt;/a&gt; of both BERT-SPC and BERT-ADA.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Node similarity with graph embeddings using Node2Vec</title>
      <link>https://nadjet.github.io/blog/posts/neo4j_gembeds/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Mar 2020 13:33:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nadjet.github.io/blog/posts/neo4j_gembeds/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I computed graph embeddings on Athletes in a graph modelling &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.kaggle.com/heesoo37/120-years-of-olympic-history-athletes-and-results&#34;&gt;Olympic Games&lt;/a&gt; in &lt;a href=&#34;https://neo4j.com/&#34;&gt;Neo4j&lt;/a&gt;. I was then able to compute the most similar Athletes to any given Athlete using &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/VHRanger/nodevectors&#34;&gt;Node2Vec&lt;/a&gt;. I could then visually appreciate this similarity by looking at the corresponding subgraph subsuming the related nodes and their edges.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Uploading pre-existing datasets in Neo4j: lessons learnt</title>
      <link>https://nadjet.github.io/blog/posts/neo4j_olympic/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Mar 2020 15:56:33 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nadjet.github.io/blog/posts/neo4j_olympic/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently I developed a proof-of-concept to model and query data with Neo4J starting from a pre-existing dataset. I also performed a training session for loading and querying a Neo4j graph database from a pre-existing &amp;ldquo;toy&amp;rdquo; dataset. Here is what I learnt from those exercises.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Anonymization</title>
      <link>https://nadjet.github.io/blog/draft_posts/anonymization/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2020 12:15:07 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nadjet.github.io/blog/draft_posts/anonymization/</guid>
      <description>Anonymization What is anonymization? Anonymization means the processing of personal data in order to irreversibly prevent identification. If the personal information is recoverable, say because:
 it is held in a separate resource, or the information hiding techniques employed make it recoverable, or the data still contains information that makes the person identifiable or partially identifiable, or the different bits of information can be cross-referenced within the dataset or across different datasets to infer the identity of the person.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My projects for Data Science Master Students</title>
      <link>https://nadjet.github.io/blog/posts/masters_topics/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Jan 2020 11:24:13 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nadjet.github.io/blog/posts/masters_topics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Here are the projects I propose to &lt;a href=&#34;https://estudios.uoc.edu/es/masters-universitarios/data-science/presentacion&#34;&gt;Data Science Master&lt;/a&gt; students for their final project this semester. They range from text mining, concept mining, question answering to natural language generation. Most of them will be based on DBPedia/Wikipedia datasets.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Seq2seq Natural Language Generation</title>
      <link>https://nadjet.github.io/blog/posts/seq2seq_nlg/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2019 14:33:22 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nadjet.github.io/blog/posts/seq2seq_nlg/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I implemented a seq2seq Natural Language Generator using the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.fast.ai/&#34;&gt;fastai&lt;/a&gt; library and the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.macs.hw.ac.uk/InteractionLab/E2E/&#34;&gt;2017 e2e NLG challenge&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/tuetschek/e2e-dataset&#34;&gt;dataset&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mining and Geovisualization of Domain Specific DBPedia Concepts</title>
      <link>https://nadjet.github.io/blog/posts/concept_mining_environment/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Nov 2019 22:32:07 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nadjet.github.io/blog/posts/concept_mining_environment/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I extracted domain specific concepts from DBPedia and showed them on an interactive map of the world. The geolocalization was done using Geonames. This was a fun project to do.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Setting up DBPedia/Geonames on OpenLink Virtuoso</title>
      <link>https://nadjet.github.io/blog/posts/bulk_upload_virtuoso/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Nov 2019 20:21:58 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nadjet.github.io/blog/posts/bulk_upload_virtuoso/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this post, I explain how to setup DBPedia and Geonames locally on Virtuoso Triplestore.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to bulk upload data into Neo4j Community Edition</title>
      <link>https://nadjet.github.io/blog/posts/bulk_upload_neo4j_community/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Sep 2019 15:56:33 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nadjet.github.io/blog/posts/bulk_upload_neo4j_community/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this post, I explain how to upload concepts and relations into Neo4J Community Edition.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to install DBPedia Spotlight Locally</title>
      <link>https://nadjet.github.io/blog/posts/install_dbpedia_spotlight/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Sep 2019 06:24:17 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nadjet.github.io/blog/posts/install_dbpedia_spotlight/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this post I explain how to install on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dbpedia-spotlight.org/&#34;&gt;DBPedia Spotlight&lt;/a&gt; on your local computer. DBPedia Spotlight is a tool that annotates mentions of DBPedia concepts in text. It is not in active development but can still be useful for Proof-of-Concept Demonstrators.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Multi-label classification</title>
      <link>https://nadjet.github.io/blog/posts/multi_label_classification/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Apr 2019 18:07:41 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nadjet.github.io/blog/posts/multi_label_classification/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have trained a classifier with fine tuned embedding language model that assigns content labels to basic restaurant descriptions using the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.fast.ai/&#34;&gt;fastai&lt;/a&gt; library.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About myself</title>
      <link>https://nadjet.github.io/blog/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nadjet.github.io/blog/about/</guid>
      <description>My name is Nadjet Bouayad-Agha. I am a specialist in Natural Language Processing. I am particularly interested in Natural Language Generation (NLG) and Knowledge Engineering.
I like solving real-world problems in a variety of domains using abundant data, open-source resources and cutting edge Deep Learning and NLP techniques.
I enjoy keeping up to date with the latest progress and outbreaks in my field and am a regular reviewer at NLP conferences.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>